<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joel Riphagen</title>
    <link>http://joelrip.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Joel Riphagen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://joelrip.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have had a 15-year career as a government policy and finance analyst. During that time, I advised politicians on budgetary and policy matters, worked in public-private partnerships to redevelop blighted communities, and administered programs to provide assistance to low-income families. I am proud of my accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am now going about public service in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among other things, I am the Captain of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codeforsacramento.org/&#34;&gt;Code for Sacramento&lt;/a&gt;, a community organization dedicated to improving people&amp;rsquo;s access to government information and services. This involves a lot of fundraising, event organizing, and volunteer herding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I really love is data analysis and visualization. I get a geeky kind of pleasure from turning data into information, information into knowledge, and knowledge into wisdom (a.k.a. climbing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DIKW_pyramid&#34;&gt;DIKW Pyramid&lt;/a&gt;), and using that newly-discovered wisdom to help people.  This website collects my explorations into data analysis and visualization for the public good. Enjoy! And let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Plain Markdown Post</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2016-12-30-hello-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 21:49:57 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2016-12-30-hello-markdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post written in plain Markdown (&lt;code&gt;*.md&lt;/code&gt;) instead of R Markdown (&lt;code&gt;*.Rmd&lt;/code&gt;). The major differences are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You cannot run any R code in a plain Markdown document, whereas in an R Markdown document, you can embed R code chunks (&lt;code&gt;```{r}&lt;/code&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A plain Markdown post is rendered through &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/configuration/&#34;&gt;Blackfriday&lt;/a&gt;, and an R Markdown document is compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rmarkdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://pandoc.org&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many differences in syntax between Blackfriday&amp;rsquo;s Markdown and Pandoc&amp;rsquo;s Markdown. For example, you can write a task list with Blackfriday but not with Pandoc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;task-list&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; checked disabled class=&#34;task-list-item&#34;&gt; Write an R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; disabled class=&#34;task-list-item&#34;&gt; Write a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; disabled class=&#34;task-list-item&#34;&gt; &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; disabled class=&#34;task-list-item&#34;&gt; Profit!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Blackfriday does not support LaTeX math and Pandoc does. I have added the MathJax support to this theme (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yihui/hugo-lithium-theme&#34;&gt;hugo-lithium-theme&lt;/a&gt;) but there is a caveat for plain Markdown posts: you have to include inline math expressions in  a pair of escaped parentheses &lt;code&gt;\&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;( \)&lt;/code&gt; instead of dollar signs &lt;code&gt;$ $&lt;/code&gt;, e.g. &lt;code&gt;\(S_n = \sum_{i=1}^n X_i\)&lt;/code&gt;. For R Markdown posts, you can use &lt;code&gt;$ $&lt;/code&gt; to write inline math expressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating a new post, you have to decide whether the post format is Markdown or R Markdown, and this can be done via the &lt;code&gt;rmd&lt;/code&gt; argument of the function &lt;code&gt;blogdown::new_post()&lt;/code&gt;, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;blogdown::new_post(&amp;quot;Post Title&amp;quot;, rmd = FALSE)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can embed an R code chunk like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(cars)
##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00
fit &amp;lt;- lm(dist ~ speed, data = cars)
fit
## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = dist ~ speed, data = cars)
## 
## Coefficients:
## (Intercept)        speed  
##     -17.579        3.932&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;including-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Including Plots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also embed plots. See Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pie&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;par(mar = c(0, 1, 0, 1))
pie(
  c(280, 60, 20),
  c(&amp;#39;Sky&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Sunny side of pyramid&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Shady side of pyramid&amp;#39;),
  col = c(&amp;#39;#0292D8&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#F7EA39&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#C4B632&amp;#39;),
  init.angle = -50, border = NA
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:pie&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/figures/pie-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;A fancy pie chart.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: A fancy pie chart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD




/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Diverse Is My Neighborhood? Mapping Ethnic Diversity in Sacramento, Part I</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-24-how-diverse-is-my-neighborhood-mapping-ethnic-diversity-in-sacramento-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-24-how-diverse-is-my-neighborhood-mapping-ethnic-diversity-in-sacramento-part-i/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Sacramento is regularly lauded as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://content.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,340694,00.html&#34;&gt;most ethnically diverse&lt;/a&gt;, or at least one of the most ethnically diverse, cities in the nation. Not just at the city level, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://priceonomics.com/the-most-and-least-segregated-cities-in-america/&#34;&gt;at the neighborhood level&lt;/a&gt; as well. More than any other American city, the members of Sacramento’s different racial and ethnic groups live and work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, like me, you live in Sacramento, you can experience this firsthand. My immediate neighbors are black, Hispanic, white, and mixed-race black/white, and my own family is mixed Asian/white. It’s a far cry from Chicago, where I attended grad school. There, the city itself is diverse, but its neighborhoods are quite segregated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the national recognition for Sacramento is deserved and appreciated, it leaves a few open questions. Among them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The City of Sacramento’s population is about 480,000, but the urbanized area contains more than 1.7 million people, and the Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) more than 2.2 million. How diverse is the metro area as a whole?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sacramento has a high average diversity across its census tracts, but how much variation is there among the tracts? Which are the most and least diverse tracts in the area?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To the extent there’s variation among different areas of the metro, what causes this variation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does the diversity of one’s neighborhood affect how they experience life in the metro area? How do the characteristics of diverse tracts and the people in them differ from those of less diverse tracts?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I’d use these questions as an opportunity to exercise my analytical skills and play with some data, while also sharing any insight I gain with the wider world. As I think through the issues, it’s clear that coming up with any kind of answer to the questions in that final bullet point above could take a lot of work. So this post is subtitled, perhaps optimistically, Part I. We’ll see how far we get today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-sacramento-area&#34;&gt;What is “The Sacramento Area”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any city, the boundaries of “Sacramento” are fuzzy. Of course the municipality has a bright line boundary, as does the county. But there is a larger urbanized area around both of them (excluding a large rural part of Sacramento County), and there are various defined multi-county designations at the local and federal level, including the census-designated Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) and Combined Statistical Area (CSA), as well as the jurisdictional boundary of the regional Sacramento Area Council of Governments (SACOG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which one, if any, will we use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;many-sacramentos&#34;&gt;Many Sacramentos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/SacBoundaries.png&#34; alt=&#34;SacBoundaries&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A casual examination suggests that the largest of these areas, which incorporate the rural area surrounding Sacramento, are far too large for my purposes. Census MSAs and CSAs follow county boundaries, and in their effort to include everyone who could be considered a resident of the Sacramento area, they include many who could not.  Certainly Tahoe residents would not think of themselves as Sacramento-area residents.  And Yuba City residents, while some may commute to Sacramento, live further away from downtown Sacramento than residents of Vacaville and Lodi, which no geography considers to be part of the Sacramento area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the official designations, the Urbanized Area is closest to what I think of as Sacramento, with perhaps Davis and Woodland thrown in as well. We’ll focus on census tracts roughly in the square surrounding downtown Sacramento that includes these areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-diversity&#34;&gt;What is “Diversity”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To measure ethnic diversity, we’ll use the Multigroup Entropy Index (aka Theil’s H or the Information Theory Index) as described in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.census.gov/hhes/www/housing/housing_patterns/multigroup_entropy.pdf&#34;&gt;this work done for the Census Department&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, we categorize residents into one of six broad groups: non-Hispanic white, Hispanic, black, Asian/Pacific Islander, Native American, and mixed-race/other. A perfectly diverse census tract (scoring 1.0 on the Index) would contain exactly the same number of residents from each of these groups. A perfectly homogeneous (non-diverse) census tract (scoring 0 on the Index) would contain only members of one of these groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In simplifying diversity to this one number, we are of course losing a lot of detail. Chinese, Indians, and Filipinos are all lumped into one group, as are Russians, Irish, and Italians, as is anyone who identifies as Hispanic, regardless of race. But this level of categorization creates an easily-understood measure that can serve as a starting point for more detailed analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-diverse-are-the-census-tracts&#34;&gt;How Diverse are the Census Tracts?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s the basic map of Sacramento-area census tract diversity, using the index described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ethnic-diversity-in-the-sacramento-area&#34;&gt;Ethnic Diversity in the Sacramento Area&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/SacDivTracts.png&#34; alt=&#34;SacDivTracts&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you a sense of what the colors mean, I’ve highlighted a purple tract in Folsom with a green border. This tract scores a 0.716 on the diversity index. It is 20% white, 47% black, 26% Hispanic, 2% Asian, 1% Native American, and 5% other/multiracial. As the map shows, tracts with this or a greater level of diversity are common in the Sacramento area, though this particular tract is uncommon in that it is Folsom Prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A review of this map confirms that much of the Sacramento area is very diverse, including such disparate areas as Rancho Cordova, Oak Park, the Florin-Vineyard area, Elk Grove, Meadowview, the Pocket, West Sacramento, Natomas, North Sacramento, and Foothill Farms. While the ethnically diverse areas certainly do include the lower-income areas of the city, they include relatively wealthy areas as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diverse area is pierced, however, by a less-diverse wedge extending from Land Park and Curtis Park, through East Sacramento, and out between Interstate 80 and Highway 50 to Citrus Heights, Roseville, and Folsom, where the ethnic diversity begins to fade in all directions. The notable pockets of diversity between 80 and 50 are the western portion of Arden Arcade, Sac State, and of course Folsom Prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is another way to visualize the variation in diversity among census tracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/SacDivHist.png&#34; alt=&#34;SacDivHist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart shows all of the census tracts in the SACOG area, sorted by diversity. It shows over 70 very highly diverse census tracts (diversity score between 0.8 and 0.9), a number of diverse census tracts down to a diversity score of about 0.5, and then a gradual decline down to the lowest diversity scores on the left. It also shows that the mean diversity score of the census tracts in the City of Sacramento is quite a bit higher than the mean over the entire SACOG area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the chart and the map show, there’s a lot of diversity in Sacramento’s diversity. But at this point we just have a range of numbers. Let’s translate some of these numbers into more concrete examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sacramento-s-most-and-least-diverse-tracts&#34;&gt;Sacramento’s Most and Least Diverse Tracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five most diverse census tracts in the Sacramento area are all located within the city limits, but are otherwise quite different from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;locations-of-sacramento-s-most-diverse-census-tracts&#34;&gt;Locations of Sacramento’s Most Diverse Census Tracts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/SacHighTracts.png&#34; alt=&#34;SacHighTracts&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/MostDiverseBar.png&#34; alt=&#34;MostDiverseBar&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census Tract 65&lt;/strong&gt;, the most diverse census tract in the area, is bisected by Interstate 80. South of the interstate, the tract encompasses the north side of Del Paso Heights, including Grant High. This is one of the traditionally low-income neighborhoods of the city. North of the interstate, the tract is characterized by newer single-family developments built largely within the last 20 years. This area has been subject to the City’s inclusionary ordinance during its development, which required a certain portion of the new housing to be affordable to lower income residents. While this is all contained within one tract, the interstate divides it into two distinct neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census Tract 7&lt;/strong&gt; is the center of downtown Sacramento, including Old Sacramento, Chinatown, the Downtown Plaza, and soon the new Kings Arena. Its diversity stems in large part from the presence of the county jail, but the tract also includes Asian retirees in Chinatown, residents of high-rise public housing, and more well-off residents of newly remodeled Old Sacramento lofts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census Tract 96.10&lt;/strong&gt; is in the Valley Hi/North Laguna area on the south side of the City, next to but not including Cosumnes River College. It is wedged between the lower-income Meadowview and Parkway areas to the north and the higher-income Elk Grove to the south. It has also been subject to the City’s inclusionary ordinance during its recent development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census Tract 22&lt;/strong&gt; is West Land Park, and combines two very different populations: the relatively well-off residents of the single family housing toward the south end of the tract, and the low-income residents of the two large public housing projects at the north end of the tract. The public housing and the neighboring industrial area are slated for redevelopment, and it will be interesting to follow the effect of this redevelopment on the area’s diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census Tract 70.16&lt;/strong&gt; is in North Natomas, which developed rapidly over the last 20 years, and has also been subject to the City’s inclusionary ordinance. It is largely single-family homes of varying size, with a few mixed-income apartment complexes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most striking feature of these five tracts is their great variety. They include the wealthy and the poor, prisoners and students, old housing and new construction. Some are physically segregated, and others are not. Three of them gained economic diversity from the City’s inclusionary ordinance, which may also have influenced their ethnic diversity. I have a thousand questions I want to ask of the data about their similarities and differences, and I hope to do that in an upcoming post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for now let’s move on to the area’s least diverse census tracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;locations-of-sacramento-s-least-diverse-census-tracts&#34;&gt;Locations of Sacramento’s Least Diverse Census Tracts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/SacLowTracts.png&#34; alt=&#34;SacLowTracts&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2015/02/LeastDiverseBar.png&#34; alt=&#34;LeastDiverseBar&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the five most diverse census tracts in the area, the five most homogeneous tracts are located in close physical proximity to each other in suburban Roseville and Lincoln in Placer County. These five tracts are noticeably less diverse than even the tracts around them, and a quick analysis reveals a likely reason why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census Tracts 210.39 and 210.40&lt;/strong&gt; surround the Sun City Roseville, Timber Creek, and Sierra Pines golf courses. Similarly, &lt;strong&gt;Census Tracts 236, 237, and 238&lt;/strong&gt; roughly define Sun City Lincoln Hills. What unites them all, other than their proximity to a well-manicured fairway, is that they are all retirement communities developed by Del Webb. It seems that this particular vision of suburban retirement appeals to a particular group of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-have-we-learned&#34;&gt;What Have We Learned?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this post has just scratched the surface of Sacramento’s diversity, we have learned a few things. The City itself is indeed more ethnically diverse than the rest of the area on average, but there is a lot of diversity in the areas around the City. Conversely, there are areas of homogeneity within the City as well. The ethnic diversity of Sacramento’s census tracts ranges from areas of the City with almost equal populations of non-Hispanic whites, blacks, Hispanics, and Asians to very homogeneous suburban retirement communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These facts aren’t surprising, but the variety of Sacramento’s most diverse census tracts is. They’re geographically dispersed, and the reasons for their diversity vary. There are a thousand more questions to be asked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do the most diverse tracts differ economically from the more homogeneous tracts, and from each other? Are average salaries higher or lower? What about housing prices and rents?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does a neighborhood’s ethnic diversity have an effect on crime rate or the types of crimes committed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are educational attainment levels different for populations in diverse tracts than for populations in homogeneous tracts?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do residents’ attitudes vary with neighborhood diversity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I’ll be able to explore these questions and more in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Game of Thrones Baby Names on the Rise in California</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-23-game-of-thrones-baby-names-on-the-rise-in-california/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-23-game-of-thrones-baby-names-on-the-rise-in-california/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Baby Arya is coming!  (As is winter.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working collaboratively with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdph.ca.gov/&#34;&gt;California Department of Public Health (CDPH)&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve done an analysis and visualization of baby names given in California from 2009 through 2013. In particular, we checked out how many parents were inspired to name their bundles of joy after characters in George RR Martin’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.georgerrmartin.com/book-category/?cat=song-of-ice-and-fire&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Song of Ice and Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; book series (aka &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hbo.com/game-of-thrones#/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on HBO) over that five year period.  The takeaway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect to be voting for President Arya in 2056.  And that might even be a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As CDPH noted on its tumblr page (Yes, the state dept. of public health uses tumblr! Who knew?), the popularity of Arya as a girl’s name more than quadrupled from 2009 to 2013, with 152 so christened last year.  Khaleesi is also on the rise, while Daenerys really isn’t.  This is kind of like wanting to name your kid after Dr. J and naming him Doctor instead of Julius, but to each his or her own.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://cdphopendata.tumblr.com/post/94107141030/hbos-game-of-thrones-inspires-baby-names&#34;&gt;You can check out CDPH’s post, complete with my chart of girls named for Game of Thrones characters, right here.&lt;/a&gt;  I’ve also reproduced the chart below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2014/08/Girl GOT Stacked 2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Girls GOT Stacked 2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s much more in the data than CDPH discussed.  For example, in addition to the female name chart, I’ve produced a male name chart as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://joelrip.github.io/img/2014/08/Boys GOT Stacked 2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Boys GOT Stacked 2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note: The Game of Thrones names you will not see on this chart?  Jaime and Jon.  There are a couple hundred new boys named Jaime in CA each year, mostly unrelated to the TV show or books.  Throwing them into the boy name chart would have swamped all the other interestingness.  And while Jon is much less popular than Jaime, with only 30 or so each year, it’s showing no pattern of increase, and it would be surprising if many of them were related to Game of Thrones.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do we see in these charts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While Arya was far and away the most popular Game of Thrones name for girls, it was also the most popular name for boys, with 108 receiving that name in the past 5 years.  However, while female Aryas are skyrocketing, male Aryas are on the decline.  I suspect we’re passing the experimental stage of the name, where the avant garde book readers were using it as they saw fit, to the mainstream stage, where the weekly HBO watchers are associating it with the plucky girl they see on their screens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shae (Tyrion Lannister’s lover, for those who aren’t following along) is also a gender-bending name, though it’s holding steady at 2 to 3 boys per year and 10 to 15 girls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s always someone willing to go the extra mile to give their kid the interesting name.  In the last five years, California has welcomed a Drogo, a Gendry, a Jorah, a Stannis, nine Theons, seven Tyrions, two Tywins…and last year, someone saw fit to name their newborn baby boy Joffrey.  I do not want to know how his parents met.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But there’s still lots of opportunity for uniqueness!  No one in California has yet decided to name their child Cersei, Melisandre, Margaery, Ygritte, Jeyne, Rickon, Petyr, Davos, Varys, Eddard, Viserys, or Hodor!  Hodor‘s just sitting out there waiting to be scooped up!  Tell your expecting friends!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is of course much more to delve into in the name data, and CDPH doesn’t yet have it up on their site in an easily-searchable format.  So if you’ve got a particular question about it, let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>City of Sacramento Open Budget Project</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-23-city-of-sacramento-open-budget-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-23-city-of-sacramento-open-budget-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the past few months volunteering with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codeforsacramento.org/&#34;&gt;Code4Sac&lt;/a&gt;, the local &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codeforamerica.org/&#34;&gt;Code for America&lt;/a&gt; brigade.  This is an organization of hacker types who are trying to use their skills for the public good, working to free government data for the people to use as they see fit.  And if you see the word &amp;ldquo;hacker&amp;rdquo; and immediately think Sneakers or War Games, think again.  Modern hackers work with the government as often as not, and Code4Sac is sponsored by the City of Sacramento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on, the City of Sacramento Open Budget Project, is an effort to take the city&amp;rsquo;s budget document, which is published online only in PDF format, and convert it into machine-readable data.  This means you can open it up in your spreadsheet or database or other analysis program and start exploring the numbers, creating your own charts, and making your own connections.  And we&amp;rsquo;ve finally hit the point at which it can be revealed to the world.  So here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://codeforsacramento.org/your-city-your-budget/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City of Sacramento Open Budget Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also check out our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1wUiROCaNRgMAwZLxylvuEGge0HOI5O2b0zVHdo5ZAxg/edit&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this particular project, all the technical work was finished before I even got involved, so I can&amp;rsquo;t take credit for the data conversion or the visualizations on the project page (that credit goes to Jay Venti).  Instead, I added some good old-fashioned project management skills to help carry the thing over the finish line.  Still, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to be involved in data work for the public benefit.  More to come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Editor&amp;rsquo;s Note January 2017: After this initial foray into opening city budget data, Code for Sacramento convinced the City of Sacramento to release its budget data onto its &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.cityofsacramento.org/home&#34;&gt;open data portal&lt;/a&gt;, enabling a &lt;a href=&#34;http://openbudgetsac.org/&#34;&gt;much more sophisticated version of this project&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Childhood Vaccination in Sacramento</title>
      <link>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-23-mapping-childhood-vaccination-in-sacramento/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://joelrip.github.io/post/2017-01-23-mapping-childhood-vaccination-in-sacramento/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve created &lt;a href=&#34;http://joelriphagen.net/SacVaccination1314.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;an interactive map&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of childcare facilities and Kindergartens in the Sacramento area, color-coded by the percentage of students that are unvaccinated due to Personal Belief Exemptions (PBEs).  Based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdph.ca.gov/programs/immunize/Pages/ImmunizationLevels.aspx&#34;&gt;2013-14 data&lt;/a&gt; from the California Department of Public Health.  &lt;em&gt;[Note: Not smartphone friendly.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Editor&amp;rsquo;s Note January 2017: This map was created almost a year before the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2015/02/06/us/california-measles-vaccines-map.html&#34;&gt;New York Times&amp;rsquo; map&lt;/a&gt; using the same data. Admittedly, theirs is prettier, and it&amp;rsquo;s statewide.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
